Have you ever seen one like before?
>> This is sort of like the ballet version
of a famous Beyonce song. You know,
everybody knows the famous Beyonce
songs. They can all sing along. Well,
this is a very famous ballet.
Well, for me there's something missing.
The be the music is [music] gorgeous.
The choreography is beautiful. Like you
said, it's soft and it's danyy and it's
pretty, but there's something missing.
>> [music]
>> Heat. Heat.
Ballet, you fall in love with it. Your
body falls in love with it.
>> Ballet is such a challenge and [music] I
love the challenge.
>> When I'm on stage, it's like no one can
stop me.
>> It's like singing with your body.
>> I knew that if I kept dancing, [music] I
could be like the ballerina on the
stage.
Mainly [music] it's a white world.
All the ballet company, [music]
the core has to be Lily White and the
soloist has to have what they prescribe
as being the ballet body.
So [music] it hasn't changed.
I grew up in Treport, Louisiana. And um
the first ballet I ever went to see, I
was 3 years old and it was Dance Theater
of Harlem.
I sat on my mom's lap and I like put my
hands on the back of the chair in front
of me and I was just looking up and like
I didn't blink the entire time for like
however long, you know, an hour and a
half. I was just so [music] like into
the show.
I knew that if I kept dancing, I could
be [music] like the ballerina on the
stage.
[music]
The Dance Theater of Harlem Company came
back to Streetport in 2002. [music]
It was my senior year of high school. I
actually took company class with them
and I was so nervous. I was like, "Oh my
gosh, all these beautiful black
ballerinas."
Afterwards, they asked me if I would
like to come to their summer intensive
for 6 weeks in [music] New York City.
And I say, "Well, of course."
>> And one, two, one. That's it. Five. And
>> And then a year later, Mr. Mitchell
[music] asked me to be in the company.
Even after I was accepted into the
ensemble, um I told my parents and they
were like, "You are not moving to New
York City. You know that you're going to
college." So I ended up actually going
there for 2 weeks because they didn't
want me to go to [music] New York.
As young African-American dancers,
sometimes [music] they're discouraged
from even trying ballet because it's not
the norm.
People would rather push you towards
something that's going to make money or
[music] that's going to, you know, give
you fame.
They will always tell someone to go out
for the NFL cuz it's going to make you
millions of dollars. They're not going
to tell you, "Oh, go, you know, trying
to be a ballerina and struggle all your
life."
>> The parents don't go to ballet. They
don't see it [music] as an opportunity
for their youngsters.
And I think if they saw more of
themselves on stage, more of them in
ballet companies, more of them on
television doing [music] just that, they
would be encouraged. But I think they
get deterred because of the lack of
opportunity.
And so I cried every single day and I
called home and I was like, I don't want
to be here. I want to go to New York.
And so they finally came and got me
[music] and let me come up here. And
they were like, you get one chance.
And [music] that's all I needed. I mean,
I used to love when people told me I
couldn't do something. I'd be like, let
me show you cuz I'm going to do it.
My mother works for the school district
in Fulton County in Georgia. [music]
So every now and then she would get like
free comp tickets to come see like a
dress rehearsal of Atlanta Ballet.
>> [music]
>> I saw Atlanta Festival Ballet perform
the Nutcracker and there was [music]
this dancer named Kila Harvey. She was
like the first black ballerina that I
ever saw and she did do drop
and I was just like I want to do ballet.
When I was a student at Atlanta Festival
Ballet [music] my senior year in high
school, I got to be Clara for the
Nutcracker.
[music]
And there was this unfortunate incident
where me and another girl were supposed
to be Claire who was Caucasian.
And [music] there was this big thing
about her not wanting to share a costume
with me.
[music]
Oh, that was like the moment where I was
like, really? I haven't even left home
yet and this [music] is what I'm
getting.
That was the first big eye opener that I
had as a dancer.
It really wasn't her reaction that made
it disheartening. is that the the
company didn't stand up for me. [music]
>> I was an avid movie fan. I was a huge
fan of Sidice [music]
and I looked at what she was doing and
in my little 9year-old 10year-old
[music] self, I thought, "Oh, I can do
that.
So, I took a friend uh and we went to
register at all of the downtown schools.
I didn't know at the time that the
schools were not open to me.
God bless my mother. She didn't tell me
the reality because it would have been
very upsetting to a little 10year-old to
realize that you're in a city like
Philadelphia and you have limited
opportunity.
At that time, Philadelphia had in the
junior high and high schools had what
they called clubs. I was in the ballet
club.
When I graduated [music] from high
school, I was determined that I was
going to go to New York and dance.
Leap forward [music] a number of years
and I go to School of American Ballet.
You had to audition. Thank goodness
[music] I was one of the ones to get in.
A company was formed in New York
originally called Ballet Americana.
We rehearsed for about a year before we
went to to Britain
and oh it was wonderful. We had amazing
[music]
choreography. We had wonderful costumes
and sets. [music]
We went over on the uh the France, the
Elder France, and oh that was so
glamorous because at that time you dress
for dinner. Uh we were sort of little
celebrities because we were a ballet
[music] company.
They changed our name from Ballet
Americana to New York Negro Ballet
because they wanted the audiences to
think we [music] were exotic
and if we weren't just another American
company uh they wanted to be clear.
[music]
We did a lot of modern things, but
Bluebird Padilla [music] was something
that was familiar. And when we hit that
stage, nobody ran screaming out of the
theater, said, "Oh god, they shouldn't
be doing this." or you know it was um it
was wonderful warm applause [music] and
acceptance.
When I came back to New York, I took
classes with with what were principal
dancers from New York City Ballet. I was
in the front line, in the middle in
every class. Nobody was being kind to me
cuz ballet classes, people are not being
kind to you.
No teacher I've ever studied with put
people without ability on the front
line.
I was certainly up to the work. Uh
there's, you know, when you're raised to
believe the harder you work, uh you
know, you're skilled at what you do,
you're educated at it, uh you should
have have a shot.
There was nothing. uh went to auditions.
Um it didn't [music] matter.
I would understand if you don't have the
quality. Uh you don't have to like every
dancer.
Uh if you don't have the ability,
but when you're not given the
opportunity simply skin deep, that's a
terrible problem.
I was born in New York City in Manhattan
and I grew up in Harlem.
We lived up in the Dunar apartments.
My mother was a stay-at-home mom. She
took me to concerts and ballet and
museums.
She took me to see the ballet rooster
Monte Carlo.
The light just comes into a glow on the
gold curtain and the conductor picks up
his baton and the rousing mazerk of
Capellia starts and I started crying
because it was so exciting. [music] It
was so wonderful and that it was
overwhelming.
And then on my 9inth birthday, [music]
it was a a present, my first ballet
lesson.
Everyone wanted to dance in ballet roose
to Monte Carlo. They had every year a
huge audition. Everybody came. I was
never accepted.
One of the young men in the school who
had been a friend took me aside and he
said, um, the next audition was coming
up. He said, "Don't don't take that
audition because you just will never get
in the ballet roose. They can't take you
in that company cuz they travel."
I was extremely disappointed because I
realized this thing has come up now. I'm
[music] really hitting the truth. And I
said to myself, well, you certainly
aren't going to get anywhere if you sit
down and feel sorry about about this
situation or feel sorry if you you have
to keep going. So I got put my toe shoes
and my little press my little ballet
skirt and went off to the audition
anyway. Sergey Denim, the [music]
director, he stood up with his he said,
"How would you like to become a member
of the Bal Rust Monte Carlo?
>> [music]
>> And it was the third year that I
actually got the walls feed.
[music]
>> I think I went two years with no
incident in traveling at all.
The south was getting uptight. You know,
in 54 [music] they desegregated the
schools. Well, the reaction to all that
was growing and coming [music] to a
crisis head.
Then I ended up in Montgomery, Alabama
one time and I mean I was going to dance
and the bus comes into the town and
there are all these sheets and hoods all
over the street
and Montgomery, Alabama was in the midst
of a [music] glue clan convention and
the Valley Roose bus comes in.
So we [music] get to the hotel. I just
went and to the dining room and when I
went in the room I saw all these people,
[music] little families and children and
the people being so attentive to their
little children and hugging them and
seeing [music] the food was right. And I
thought, "Oh, is this just like a
holiday? These isn't this nice?"
And I pulled out the chair to sit down
at the table and on the empty chair next
to me was all the hoods and gowns. So it
was this these were all clan people in
the dining room and I thought oh my
goodness all these lovely little
children. I thought I felt so sad that
you know just to realize that all that
love they're giving them but they're
spreading the hatred to them. You know,
somebody came to me and said, "Raven,
you don't go to the theater. Go back up
in the room and shut the door and lock
it and stay [music] in there. Don't open
the door for anybody." So, I went back
upstairs. And the company went and had
the performance. And that night as the
dust [music] came in, I was there was a
window out that looked out kind of like
a little ravine and I saw
first and last [music] and only time in
my life I saw the them burning the
cross.
[music]
They decided I should go back to New
York because they didn't know what was
going to happen
here. I had been in the ballet roose all
these years cultivating
the classical meme and having solos and
and suddenly someone came to me and said
you've gone as far as you can in the
company and uh after all they said we
can't have a black white swan.
She said why don't you get [music] out
and get a little group together and do
African dance.
Well, that's what you don't tell people
who've striven just to do what [music]
they do if they want to be a classical
dancer. And you spend so much time and
effort because the whole thing was prove
it. You these people can't dance
classical dance.
I was just so tired. I could feel it. I
just felt exhausted physically and
emotionally. So, I said, I just have to
stop for a while.
I graduated from U Arts in 2012 with a
degree in dance education with a major
in ballet
and I went to so many auditions I
couldn't even tell you at one and
they're all so expensive. I had to call
family members a couple of times to ask
if they if I could have some money to go
to auditions.
My young arts number is 08002569/101.
The title of my piece is dream.
>> [music]
>> the training is very expensive. Um, my
parents sacrificed a lot to [music] keep
me in dance.
I'm so grateful that my parents were
able to do that, but everybody's [music]
parents aren't able to afford that.
Didn't get anything, so I had to go back
home.
I had like a regular person's job. I was
a waitress, [music] you know, to even
out and pay help pay for those student
loans.
I kind of lost focus when I went home
this past year and I was getting out of
shape. I knew after that experience in
high school that color was going to be
an issue. I didn't want anything else to
be an issue. So, I stopped eating red
meat cuz I didn't want weight to be an
issue. [music] I didn't want them to be
like, "Well, not only are you black, but
you're big, too." So,
>> [music]
>> Well, I'm at Joffrey Summer intensive in
New York right now being a chaperon in
the dorms. [music]
So, one of the perks is being able to
take classes when we're available.
And you just see everyone else get a job
and you're like, why not me?
I've also heard it's the politics.
Sometimes it's not the director that
makes the decision, it's the board. And
the board is always full of people who
have
only seen ballet in one specific color.
So, they're not ready.
There's a visual element to [music]
ballet that makes people stop and makes
people think, well, I don't know if
it'll look like ballet if it doesn't
look [music] like 12 identical swans
with exactly the same bodies and the
same skin tone and the same hair tone
standing in exactly the same position.
We are doing things the same way they've
been [music] done for hund hundreds of
years. And I think the classic works
need to be performed in that [music]
that same way with that same honor to
the tradition.
And actually [music] the identicalness
of ballet is not that you literally look
the [music] same, but that you embody
the same intention, the same spirit, the
same idea, the same movement.
You can only you can only do so much
before you just like whatever I guess
I'll go back to school or [music] do
something else cuz I don't want to do
modern.
I've [music] had teachers in the past
like have you ever thought about going
to Alvin Alen? I'm like no love Alan
Alen respect them seen plenty of their
works but I don't want to be a modern
dancer. [music] And I felt like they
suggested that company just because they
were a black company. Pretty
sure if I want to do modern, there would
have been some place [music] somewhere
that I would have ended up.
I refuse to be pushed over that. I would
rather stop dancing than
be forced [music] to do modern. I would
rather put on point shoes than be
barefoot.
And when when Dance Theater of Harlem
disbanded, all those wonderful dancers
couldn't find work
because they still weren't hiring black
ballet dancers.
When um the company went on hiatus in
2004, I actually did auditions for other
companies and there were a lot of
companies who I felt, you know, wanted
to hire me, but I had to start all the
way from the beginning again. And I just
didn't really want to do that cuz I had
been working so hard and I felt like I
was at a level where I shouldn't have to
like start over as an apprentice or in
the second company.
When I see those gorgeous young women
from [music] from Dance Theater Harlem,
they could meld right into that quarter
ballet because [music]
they already have Balanchine ballets
under their belt. They have been doing
all of those ballets.
I mean, they have all the aesthetics
[music] except color.
And then they were hiring, if they hired
anybody black or woman, [music] they had
to be so fair.
And then you have people at auditions
telling you, "You're not good enough.
You don't have the right body type." By
then, you're saying those things to
yourself. Sometimes
we're still living with Balanchin's idea
of a very small head, a a small trunk,
and really long legs, and looking like
um [music] a straw.
They say ballerinas don't have large
busts. [music]
They don't have large glutes. They don't
have large legs. You know, there are so
many things that you're not supposed to
have, [music]
quote unquote, when you're a ballet
dancer.
But, you know, when you look at that
generation of dancers that that really
inspired people, who really made people
love this art form, they were short.
They had [music] flat feet, but they had
to do a certain kind of work to make
this happen. That work is [music] where
the art is.
I rested for a while and then I started
auditioning.
I went to Ballet Theater and auditioned.
I spoke to Mr. Balanchin
and I went to the Metropolitan Opera and
auditioned.
I know I was tired and disappointed
especially that I couldn't get something
else.
Women singularly have this problem more
than African-American male classical
dancers.
If you look at all the ballet companies
across the country, when they have one,
it's usually a male, you know, the
exotic [music]
looking special male.
There's something about the woman that
is makes more difficulties for them. And
I wonder if it's the sense of the
classes and being within the female
dancer,
the sense of the transcendence of
gravity and the spirit of woman, your
gazelle, yourself, [music] everything,
the white thing. And they just feel that
that's contrary to [music] what an
Africanamean
who would represent something more
vitally part of the realologies of life.
And you know the the earth, the mother
earth [music] kind of thing.
A dancer who was a part of the National
Ballet of Holland. He was one of the top
[music] dancers.
He was an African-American dancer who we
never saw. His name was Sylvester
Campbell.
He called me and he said, "I I would
like to dance [music] with you. Why
don't you come to Holland?" And I was on
my way to Holland um in the end of
August and [music] joined the National
Ballet of Holland and had a wonderful
experience and I had [music] nice roles
in these ballets.
[music]
But I [music] decided I loved America,
too. So, I thought, well, maybe I'll go
back and see. But you you want [music]
the best of both, you know, that's human
nature. And I just [music] something
deeply in me as American. And I missed a
lot of the way even though we're like
[music] plates and earthquakes rubbing
up against each other, there's a certain
sense of the energy.
It's very sad that you have [music] to
leave your home. I just never got
another job in the United States as a
dancer.
[music]
You can look at case by case um uh
examples of African-American
dancers that have made it and have
succeeded. How did they find that
training at a young age? They aren't all
from New York. They're not all, you
know, they're not all just going into
the School of American Ballet or another
wonderful school in New York. So, they,
you know, they obviously sought it out
or had good training early on in their
lives available to them.
They keep coming back to exposure as
being just so critical.
When you're a young dancer, you do look
to things that inspire you. and the very
fact of someone going before who's
accomplished.
I think it should be said and talked
about that there was back in 1955 an
African-Amean woman who had been a
ballerina.
Now, she is someone I loved
[music]
because I remember seeing her dance and
I remember being so impressed with how
she came out on stage. That's regality
of how she stood on stage. She could
jump. She had control. She had strength.
She was absolutely bubbly. And I missed
her so much when she left.
Now, why why isn't a dancer like that?
Your first soloist.
Oh my god. And she's gorgeous. [music]
She was a dancer [music] that I think I
feel understood style and artistry. She
truly worked on these things [music] as
an artist. She had these long legs. She
had the arms and she brought the arms up
[music] and she just slid that foot in a
second. That beautiful arch and I
thought, "Oh [laughter] my goodness, I
almost fainted." I said, "This is
someone." And this is the thing. Then
you're so scared they're not going to be
able to make it. And you see that talent
there.
It's Lorie [music] Anderson. See, now
these people, I didn't know them
personally, but she was the top of the
Houston Ballet. She did. She became
[music] one of their ballerinas.
[music]
We were discussing [music] us um Debbie
Austin and somebody said well she got
discouraged about and I said why did she
get discouraged? Why do any of them get
discouraged at their talented? And then
I thought to myself, yeah, I got
discouraged and I left. You know, you
forget. I mean, Misty, everyone is crazy
about Misty Copeland.
And here [music] she is now finally
doing these great ballerina roles, you
know,
[music]
and you have to have the roles in order
to grow artistically.
going all the way down. B pla 2 three
four coming up two three open to the
second on fourth same thing second
fourth fifth position imagine that it's
>> Alvin Ellie had invited me
>> to run his scholarship program
>> so I knew I had that job I purely loved
every day that I spent in the classes
>> and
there we have fondue
and [music] stretch
I came by and visited Joan's school and
we had [music] a little chat and um she
hired me to [music] uh teach her
advanced kids. That was 38 years ago.
>> Put them together. There you go. Two and
a three and a four. Pushing B. Okay. So,
I want to see that locking position.
Here we go.
Well, you know, I started my dance
school in 1960 because I thought, oh,
maybe [music] I could give someone else
the opportunity I didn't get.
I started bringing in modern dance
teachers so that the kids would not only
just know ballet, but they would know
all dance because I knew that they had
to be able to do it all.
It was like a sculpture to him. So, we
have [music] to be really clear that the
shape is clear.
Joe Myers Brown understands the
importance, especially having a
predominantly African-American company
that we are looked at with a different
kind of [music] microscope.
She wants people to see in her company
that we can do it and do it well.
>> Rosita, you want to play directly
center. Exactly.
Dolores Brown's role is is just that of
the continuum of Miss Brown to make sure
that we are the best artists we can be.
You can't walk in her class uh unpulled
together without your shoes, without
proper, you know, your toe shoes uh sewn
correctly. It just is because she knows
that people are looking at that and they
will size you up by that.
When you leave her [music] class, you
end up being educated in the essence of
what ballet represents. Don't squat.
Make sure you can feel that pressure in
the thigh. There you are. Good. Good.
Don't drop at the last moment. Go
through all the way. Stop there. Right.
All the way. I'm very torn with my
advice [music] to anybody of color who
wants to be in the ballet.
We are way behind in just our whole
attitude about
ballet [music] and people of color. We
are in the dark ages.
I still can't fathom why the major
companies are having that as a problem.
So, I don't go to New York City Ballet
anymore and I don't go to American
[music] Ballet Theater anymore.
The last time I went to [music] New York
City Ballet, I went because I wanted to
see Dancers at a Gathering, which is
[music] one of my favorite Jerome
Robbins ballets. And I said, "This was
this is my last performance that [music]
I'm witnessing this."
When I saw dance theater do Sarah,
[music]
I couldn't I couldn't applaud at the end
right away because it was so
breathtakingly beautiful. Now, why could
those girls not then join the CO ballet
of New York City Ballet?
>> [music]
>> Don't you think for a minute that if
there were people of color in numbers,
not tokens, [music] in numbers on that
stage, that there wouldn't be bottoms in
those seats.
Let's be vulgar. [music] Let's think
dollars and cents. You have an untapped
audience.
When we went to go see ABT perform Swan
Lake, there were a lot more um people of
different backgrounds there. And I think
that's account to [music] Missy Copen
and what she's brought to ABT.
Open the door, they'll walk right in.
Beautifully walk in. and it'll be rich
and it'll look like America.
And I don't I don't want to see any more
tokens. [music]
I want to see numbers now. And I hope
somebody listens to me at some point. I
doubt it, but I hope they do.
I am a flight attendant. I am flying the
friendly skies.
I was dancing with a small dance
company, but that's not where I wanted
to be. And I just feel like every time I
was trying to like make some moves, I
was getting no.
I was just like, if I have to go back to
do this small company and then work as a
waitress all day and all night, it's
[music] not going to work out. I
wouldn't be I wouldn't last.
And then a friend uh suggested flight
attendant and I was sitting there
waitressing and you know dancing and I
was like all right well let's see what
happens.
I think I'm still making the choice cuz
every now and then I struggle with the
thought of going back into dance.
I think it came to the point where I was
just mad and like
I was like, "Oh, I don't want to be here
anymore. I just want to move on. Like I
want something else."
I don't want to hate dance.
>> [music]
>> It's [music] very very competitive field
uh uh especially for women. Uh [music]
there's just no two ways about that.
Many young girls study ballet and
there just aren't [music] that many jobs
in this country.
Ballet is an exclusive [music] art form.
You know, nine10en of the people in a
classroom are not going to be
regardless. There's a classroom of white
dancers. Nine ten of them are not going
to be dancers. [music] You know, you've
got to look right. You've got to feel
right. You've got to have the ability to
count and stand in line and you've got
to have [music] something to express. I
mean, there's a lot of requirements
there.
Sometimes you're just not what they're
looking for. So then every company
before I went to the audition, I would
look and see how many African-Amean
[music]
women they had already hired. And if
they already had one, I already knew I
wasn't getting it.
Even the um the people who are doing the
auditions [music]
I feel like they look at you a little
harder.
You just got to you got to blow [music]
them out the water.
I don't know if I would call it regret,
but I do have some
some sadness for not dancing anymore.
Um,
I can't sometimes I try to ask myself,
did I try really, really hard or did I
just give up? And I still
can't honestly answer that question to
myself cuz I don't know. I mean, I went
to auditions and I tried and I made all
these sacrifices in different ways to
try to be a a dancer, but
either it just didn't work or either I
just wasn't trying hard enough. And I I
don't know.
I don't know which one it was.
So, [snorts]
>> [music]
>> When um the school opened back up, the
[music] ensemble came back and Mr.
Mitchell actually called and asked me to
come back.
Dance Theater of Harlem started off with
two ideas. To transform lives through
art for [music] young people in Harlem
and to give dancers of color a place to
mature and [music] grow into artists to
have a career as ballet dancers where
nobody said they could have one before.
>> [music]
>> So in doing those two things, Nancy
Holland actually did a third because it
[music] it enabled people to look at
this art form of ballet in a different
way to show ballet didn't have a color.
People want ballet to reflect the past,
but I think that ballet really has to
reflect the present and project the
future. And that's what the city [music]
of Harlem has been able to do.
It's so important for people to realize
what are you looking for when you go to
see ballet.
Well, people go for different reasons.
Some [music] people do go for the the
reassurance of a world that hasn't
changed.
Some people go because they're ready for
their minds to be open and to see
[music] another kind of beauty.
This is not just about ballet.
Our [music] society today is just moving
at a very, very slow pace when it comes
to diversity.
[music] You know, it can't just be Dance
Theater of Harlem that accepts dancers
of color. It has [music] to grow to
other companies.
It's going to be interesting.
>> Mhm. Because always like when you're
working with kids that don't really
>> don't really have that experience with
ballet like how do you
>> It's kind of exciting though. They just
have no idea. They're completely
oblivious that we you know in Charlotte
there is
>> there is a company there.
>> Ballet company
>> and then we're sweating so much so we
work so hard and then
>> so what do you do teach? I'm like no.
>> Especially in areas like this kids don't
really get to see um ballet that much
unless their parents are into it. And
it's like
>> they don't even know it exists
sometimes.
>> Yeah.
[music]
More breath.
and stand tall. [music]
Pull your tummyies in. First position,
chins up.
>> You know, we're in America and I think
it's very important that we represent
the diversity of [music]
American people.
>> [music]
>> Unfortunately, we audition
between 300 and 500 dancers, let's say.
And out of that, maybe there's five
maximum 10 African-American.
Uh, also uh for Hispanic, there's also
more, you know, but maybe 20 30 maximum.
So that's that's the way it [music] is.
So it's uh we cannot just complain about
it.
You just have to to be proactive you
know and say is that important to
[music] me or it's not.
Some dancers just don't come to audition
because they don't feel comfortable in
the ballet company. Maybe they have that
preconceived idea that they're not going
to be accepted.
There have been, I guess, barriers maybe
in my own mind,
uh, thinking that I can't do something
because of the color of my skin [music]
or because I don't feel like I look like
the next, you know, girl, um, next to
me.
I'm like, I can't do that. Like, I'm
never going to be able [music] to be a
soloist or a principal. Like, what am I
thinking, you know?
it it can really consume your mind and
I think it's up to us to also for them
to believe that it's going to be the
right company that they were going to be
really welcome.
Don't take just one African-American
dancer, male or female, and then you
have done diversity [music] work that
you wanted to do. It's more let's go to
discover them.
Recently [music] I talked to Vina
Johnson and she's the director of dance
theater because I trust Vina so so so
much and I know what she's the great job
she's doing and she's going to do that
it will be a good idea to make a
commitment with uh with her company to
say that every year for the next three
years I will guarantee her that I will
take two dancers [music]
from her school and that those two
dancers will come to be members of the
second company.
Our second company travels and to go to
the school and [music] that's how these
young dancers are inspired because they
see uh most of the time dancers who are
just like them, you know, and uh we need
some heroes.
>> Do you have any family members that do
ballet?
>> I'm the youngest out of three sisters,
so my two older sisters, they have some
background. Um, is dancing with like
each other isn't isn't it kind of like a
team?
>> I guess if you're dancing in a group,
you all want to be together
>> and you want all want to have the same
line and everything. So, you have to
work together and
>> just um not just think about yourself.
>> Yes.
>> How many hours a day do you practice
dancing?
>> It's 9:30 to 6 kind of that kind of
>> Next question. Don't be shy. We'll
answer.
>> Yeah. Um, at what age did you get your
point shoes? The point shoes?
>> I got my point shoes at 11.
>> I think I was 10 or 11. Your feet are
not used to it, so of course it's going
to hurt your first couple of times,
>> but it it gets easier.
The gift isn't only given to white
[music] dancers. The gift is given to
others, but they have to have the
opportunity.
What does Balanchin say? That the
ballerina should be the color of a
peeled apple, but also we know that if
the apple stays [music] peeled too long,
it turns brown. So, u you know, you got
to have different [music] shades of
apples.
I don't know that we uh I don't know the
answer as to whether we [music] actually
will see an American company that
reflects the diversity of this country.
[music]
Um I would like to think that we would.
I think that we're seeing very small
steps [music] in that direction. Uh but
but you know how quickly that happens
and
I [music] I just I just don't know. No,
we have to to make some changes. [music]
And so if part of that evolution there's
not more diversity
in a dancers population, I don't think
ballet is going to be successful. That's
really what I believe.
>> I think the future of ballet is at
stake.
We are [music] human beings. We share
things. We are identical in so many
ways. The expression, the desire to be
excellent, [music] to to inspire,
doesn't belong to one group of people or
another group of people.
The ability [music] to be the shining
example,
the example of beauty
is not restricted to [music] skin tone.
So you can have a black ballerina.
[music]
>> [music]
>> The feeling of doing ballet I just can't
explain.
[music]
that carries me to another place.
I purely [music] loved every day that I
spent in the ballet.
[music]
>> [music]
>> I knew that if I kept dancing, I could
be like the ballerina on the stage.
[music]
Heat.
Heat. Heat.